<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves out of Holland of the East Indie trade there. Containing a true copie of a Dutch treatise there published, of the grosse abuses of their maiors, the managers of their trade. Shewing that not withstanding the extreame wrongs they doe to the English nation, trading in the Indies, yet it is the iustice of God, they thriue not with it themselues. Printed this 26. of Iune. 1622.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03451</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117343</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852558</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852558</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17883</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03451)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17883)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1144:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves out of Holland of the East Indie trade there. Containing a true copie of a Dutch treatise there published, of the grosse abuses of their maiors, the managers of their trade. Shewing that not withstanding the extreame wrongs they doe to the English nation, trading in the Indies, yet it is the iustice of God, they thriue not with it themselues. Printed this 26. of Iune. 1622.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Nicholas Bourne and Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at their shops at the Exchange, and in Popes-head Pallace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Commerce --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Commerce --  East Indies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>East Indies --  Commerce --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17883:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17883:1"/>
            <p>NEVVES OVT OF HOLLAND, OF THE EAST INDIE TRADE THERE.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING A TRVE Copie of a Dutch Treatiſe there publiſhed, of the groſſe Abuſes of their MAIORS, the <hi>Managers of their</hi> TRADE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SHEWING.</hi> That notwithſtanding the extreame wrongs <hi>they doe to the Engliſh Nation, Trading in</hi> the INDIES, yet it is the juſtice of GOD, they thriue not with it themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed this</hi> 26. <hi>of</hi> IVNE. 1622.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhops at the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and in <hi>Popes-head Pallace.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17883:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17883:2"/>
            <head>The Tranſlators Epiſtle to the <hi>Indifferent Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>GEntle Reader, This</hi> Pamphlet following, came by meanes of a friende to my hand, in <hi>Dutch</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage out of <hi>Holland</hi> from the City of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> which when I had throughly peruſed, I ſuppoſe my labour could not be loſt in tranſlating it into our <hi>Engliſh</hi> tongue, becauſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> my Countrie-men, may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>2.</hi> eſpeciall conſiderations thereby: Firſt the ſmall gaine the <hi>Hollanders</hi> make by trading into the <hi>Eaſt Indies.</hi> Secondly the miſſe-governement and iniurious dealing of the <hi>Maiors,</hi> and ſuch as are appointed <hi>Governours</hi> for the trade of the <hi>Eaſt Indies</hi> by the <hi>Hollanders.</hi> If the <hi>Maiors</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> be thoſe, who Subſtitute vnder them <hi>Committies</hi> and <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for the
<pb facs="tcp:17883:3"/>governement of the Trade. They being in this <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet</hi> touched by their owne Countrie-men, of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt and vnconſcionable dealing themſelues, what <hi>Subſtitutes, Maiors</hi> &amp;c, will they appoint? but ſuch who ſhall correſpond with them in little Honeſty and leſſe Conſcience: ſo that it is to bee conſidered. in how dangerous an eſtate our <hi>Engliſh Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt Indian</hi> Companie remaine, to ſtand to the curteſie of ſuch perſons, againſt whom their owne Countrie-men doe ſo heavily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, it is apparant generally, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are wronged extreamely by the <hi>Hollanders</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt Indies;</hi> and there is ſmall hope of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe in <hi>Holland,</hi> for where Covetouſnes at home, make choyce of Officers in forraigne parts abroad, Covetouſnes will rather maintaine the extortions and oppreſsions committed by his Officers, then either redreſſe them or correct them: As by this Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation following may plainly appeare, which I leaue to the reading and conſideration of the indifferent Reader.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17883:3"/>
            <head>THE RELATION FROM THE HOLLANDERS, AC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CORDING TO THE <hi>DVTCH COPPY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas at this preſent, there is much ſpeach, and may cenſures, concerning the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and Government of the <hi>East Indie</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, as well by the <hi>Maiors</hi> on their part, as by the <hi>Aduenturers</hi> on theirs, the one making boaſt of great profits; and to haue governed the ſame ſo worthily as that they conceiue to haue
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17883:4"/>deſerved ſtill to continue and bee confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in their places. Other maintaining to the contrary, that neither the profit, nor the <hi>Maiors</hi> governement, to haue beene ſuch, as that either prayſe or thankes is due to them; but that the Adventurers, haue rather iuſt cauſe to petition to the Lords the <hi>States</hi> Generall, for redreſſe of better ordering thereof in the now next intended Patent, that thereby the profits may be advanced and more increaſed.</p>
            <p>Now the better to explaine this myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and diverſitie of opinions, wee will firſt ſet downe what hath beene the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, and next what hath beene the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of governement, to the ende that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man may iudge, what prayſe and thankes the <hi>Maiors</hi> haue deſerued.</p>
            <p>As concerning the profits, firſt is to be knowne, at what time the <hi>Adventurers</hi> did bring in and make up their Stocke, viz. in <hi>Annis.</hi> 1604. 1605. and 1606. which being receiued together faleth to bee in <hi>Anno.</hi> 1605—100. the Intereſt whereof rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned to the yeere 1622. which is for 17. yeeres after 6¼ <hi>per Cent. per An.</hi> with Intereſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17883:4"/>vpon Intereſt amounteth to little more or leſſe then —180.</p>
            <p>Now conſidering the <hi>Maiors</hi> from the yeare 1604. to the yeare 1621. haue every yeare ſent from hence to the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> a fleete to a certaine number of Ships, which are in all 18. fleetes of Ships, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more ſome times leſſe; which one with the other I reckon about halfe a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall: whereof the aſſurance ſimply go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and comming amounteth to 24. <hi>per Cent.</hi> though more muſt be given if one will enſure the trade which paſſeth from Port to Port in the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> which du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for going and comming amounteth vnto — 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6.</p>
            <p>Hereof the Intereſt reckoned at 6¼ <hi>per Cent. per An.</hi> from <hi>Anno</hi> 1605. to the yeare 1621. vntill the money bee yearely payd, which amounteth with Intereſt vpon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to little more or leſſe then —199.</p>
            <p>Whereby appeareth that the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall with the Intereſt and Aſſurance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth vnto — 695.</p>
            <p>Againſt this, is to bee reckoned what the Companie receiveth of the Enſurers,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17883:5"/>for loſſe ſuſtained by Sea as well in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as comming, which ought to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued as it coſt the Company here, which taken at the higheſt will hardly amount vnto 150. which being deducted out of the aboue ſaid 695. the Capital commeth to ſtand in with the Intereſt and aſſurance 5. Capitals, 45. <hi>per Cent.</hi> Now the <hi>Maior</hi> haue at ſeverall times delivered to the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers:</hi> 2. Capitals, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1610 — 57.½</item>
                  <item>1615 — 42.½</item>
                  <item>1618 — 62.½</item>
                  <item>1620 — 37.½</item>
               </list> Sum-200</p>
            <p>From which the Intereſt being recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the yeare 1622. after 6¾ <hi>per Cent. Ann.</hi> with intereſt vpon intereſt which amounteth vnto — 117.</p>
            <p>The reſt of the Account or Adventure, priſed in March 1622. taken at the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt is worth — 190</p>
            <p>In Summe, the Capital with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits from the beginning vnto this preſent which the <hi>Adventurers</hi> haue receiued, 5. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals. 7. <hi>per Cent.</hi> And the Capital com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17883:5"/>to ſtand in here, with the intereſt and aſſurance, as aboue appeareth, 5. Capitals and 45. <hi>per Cent.</hi> So as the <hi>Adventurers</hi> haue gained nothing neere the ſimple intereſt of 6¼ <hi>per Cent. per Ann.</hi> and ordinary aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. By this may bee gathered what profits the <hi>Adventurers</hi> haue enioyed, and how thankefull they ought to be to the <hi>Maiors,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as concerning the Governement, it is a thing certain that be it good or bad, the profits ariſe accordingly, for we dayly ſee and finde that by negligence all ill governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, a great eſtate is ſoone brought to nought: and on the contrary through a good dilligent and provident governing, great gaines ariſe out of a ſmall ſtocke or meanes: whereas during all this Patent, ſo little profit ariſeth, though great gaine is ordinarily to be made in the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> ſo as hereby may well be concluded that the ſame muſt be ſo, by reaſon of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting or governing the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now as concerning the well gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: Firſt of all is required a good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and experience, which I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17883:6"/>ſwade my ſelfe hath beene and is in many of the <hi>Maiors</hi> without all doubt, but that is not enough, except there be care and diligence withall, but what care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence can be expected from them, who are ſo continually imployed in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Offices and functions, beſides their particuler affaires, that they can ſcarce once or twiſe in a weeke, ſpend a fewe houres in this waightie buſineſſe, which indeede hath need of a conſtant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſale according as the greatneſſe and importancy thereof requireth.</p>
            <p>For if a Marchant here in Towne, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſo much to doe in his private affaires, that to doe the ſame well, hee hath very ſmall time beſides to ſpare: how much more time then doth ſo great buſineſſe require? when not onely heere within the Land, but alſo in the <hi>Indies,</hi> in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny farre remo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te partes, ſo great in Trade is driven from Port to Port, and much more may be, were it well ordered: when vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any adviſe comming thence, good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard is to be had, as alſo good information to be taken from any committie or other
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17883:6"/>perſon comming thence, that ſo thereby good adviſe may likewiſe been ſent backe from hence vpon ſure ground, and to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſo good an order for redreſſe of ought that is amiſſe there, that the Trade may flouriſh, and that thoſe places which the Company haue conquered there, may be to vs and our poſteritite in all obedience without preiudice. How great and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall a diligence this may require, and how little hath bin vſed, thoſe that haue any vnderſtanding may eaſily gather by the ſmall profits, which haue bin made.</p>
            <p>Further, is required in very <hi>Maior,</hi> that he by all meanes ſeeke to procure the common good of that which is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his charge, and not his particular: but how or wherein haue they hitherto fought the common good of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſo long as they take a libertie to ſell the Companies goods vnto themſelues, in which ſale no doubt they ſeeke their own particular profit, and not the Companies. At ſometimes one <hi>Maior</hi> buying the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies goods of another <hi>Maior;</hi> and at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other time it happeneth quite contrary,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17883:7"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> that he which was at firſt the buyer, is now become the ſeller to him that former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was the ſeller himſelfe: one may well coniecture how theſe things are thus car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, by ſuch, who it may be are not ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt as they ſhould be; what hinderance hereby befalleth the <hi>Adventurers,</hi> and what profits to the <hi>Maiors,</hi> one may well coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the ſmall profits which the <hi>Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers</hi> haue made, and the great wealth which the <hi>Maiors</hi> haue attained vnto.</p>
            <p>When as the <hi>Maiors</hi> haue bought great quantitie of the Companies goods for themſelues, is to be imagined what kinde of adviſe they will ſend to the <hi>Indies</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch goods as themſelues haue bought, and whether their adviſe ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end to their particular profits.</p>
            <p>Further may well be iudged, in what maner the <hi>Maiors</hi> ſeeke to procure the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the <hi>Adventurers,</hi> who make it a buſines to ſell their adventure for long dayes of payment, yea, oft-times more themſelues haue in the Companie, which is the cauſe that they may wiſh ill ſucceſſe to the Company, to the end that they may buy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17883:7"/>it in, the better cheape againſt the time of payment befalleth, and ſo to make their profit out of the Companies loſſes: how much ſuch <hi>Maiors</hi> doe affect that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie may proſper, may be imagined?</p>
            <p>And whether they haue not ſometime ſet out great and vnneceſſary Fleets (for many of them haue quite ſould at their adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) whereby they could not be able to deliver out any ſhares to the <hi>Adventurers:</hi> wherevnto notwithſtanding, the <hi>Maiors</hi> are by the <hi>Patent</hi> inioyned, ſo often as 5 <hi>per centum,</hi> profits may be made. All which they doe to cauſe the adventure to fall in priſe, to the end that they may buy it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine good cheape. But what hinderance hereby is befallen many <hi>Adventurers,</hi> yea, ſome vtterly vndone, is too apparant, and they ought to examine their conſciences, how free they are, and cleane herein. For might one pervſe their Bookes, no doubt thereby would be found, that many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them haue little or no adventure) at all with the Company, and it would plainely appeare, that their proviſion or factorie concernes them nearer then the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17883:8"/>profit of the ſtooke they haue there to exſpect, and therefore doe readily reſolue to the ſetting foorth of great ſhipping or fleets, when as fewer and ſmaller would haue beene ſufficient for Conqueſt, and fewer for trade from Port to Port: whereof that fleete which went through the ſtraight of <hi>Magellane</hi> was one, which fleete alone did charge the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with more then a Capital.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe the practiſe of theſe kinde of <hi>Maiors,</hi> (knowing the choyce to be in their own powers) to preferre their friends and kindred to the governement, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding thoſe that are great Adventurers, take ofttimes ſuch as are none, but ſuch as when then ſtand in nomination to be; doe then begin to buy conditionally ſo they are choſen, then their buying to ſtand: but if not, then the bargaine to be voyd: what good ſervice the Company is to exſpect by ſuch nimbling may well bee coniectured. Beſides they oft times preferre their friends, to be ſent as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitties and other Offices to the <hi>Indies,</hi> although very vnfitt thereto, whereas it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17883:8"/>highly concerneth the Company, to haue both honeſt and fitt perſons there, for hardly can it be imagined the great wrong which the Company haue ſuſtained, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the having ſo baſely vilde, &amp; proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſolent Committies in the <hi>Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, what loſſe the Companie is put vnto, by the building of ſo great and coſtly Shippes (each Chamber ſtriving which ſhall make the greateſt Ship, and all for great ſtowage, to cauſe the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter returne to be brought into their cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, thereby to procure to themſelues the greater factorie or proviſion) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well be imagined: for as well might it be done with leſſer, and Ships not ſo coſtly, and ſo the more ſtocke to bee imployed in Trade, or otherwiſe to free themſelues of their intereſt money, which great Shipps, are partly vſed to carry wood and ſtone in the <hi>Indies,</hi> for the building of the Fort <hi>Iacatra,</hi> ſome being worne and ſpent there, ſo as indeed one might haue done as well betweene this and the <hi>Indies,</hi> with halfe as many great ſhips.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17883:9"/>
            <p>Alſo many Summes of Gold haue bin ſpent in the making of divers coſtly Forts and Caſtles in the <hi>Indies,</hi> the walles being all of ſtone, being King-like workes, whereas to haue made them of Earth, as they are here in our Countrie the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, had beene as vſefull for keeping the Trade, from other Committies of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Lands: ſo had this needeles charge beene imployed in Trade, might haue advanced the Company more then a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Companie hath freely indured ſome loſſe, by reaſon of the complaint of thoſe perſons who having done the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie good ſervice, could obtaine little or no Salary for the ſame. Whereby is befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len that ſome haue put themſelues into the ſervice of other Companies of forraine Lands, to the no ſmall hinderance of this Companie, and by reaſon of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, many other honeſt yong men haue beene diſcouraged from comming into the Companies ſervice, whereas the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of good and ſufficient courſes, doth very much import the Companie. For
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17883:9"/>which cauſe wiſe and provident Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants doe both recompence and preferre their faithfull ſervants, to the end that thereby they may the longer make vſe of their good ſervice, which example ſo the <hi>Maiors</hi> would imitate in requiting their faithfull ſevants, and preferre ſome of them to the <hi>Maiorſhip,</hi> it would doe the Company much good, for that they being well experimented in the courſe of trade in the <hi>Indies,</hi> might ſerue the <hi>Maiors</hi> (who were never there) vpon all occaſions, with ſound and well grounded adviſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and this would be an induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for other honeſt yong men to put themſelues into the Companies ſervice there, and being in hope of further pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, to performe it faithfully.</p>
            <p>By theſe aboue-mentioned, and other reaſons that may be annexed hereto, is eaſie to iudge, whence it proceedeth that hitherto ſo little profit hath beene made.</p>
            <p>And that therefore the <hi>Adventurers</hi> as Petitioners, haue iuſt cauſe and reaſon to intreate the Lords the <hi>States,</hi> for better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17883:10"/>and Patent, and that they are not to bee blamed, as ſome haue gone about to doe.</p>
            <p>For Concluſion; Conſidering the Trade to the <hi>Indies,</hi> doth ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Land in generall, and the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers</hi> each in his particular, to the end that through the well ordering there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it may not fall to the grounde, but ſtand firme to vs, and to our poſteritie. It is not to be doubted, but that the Lords the <hi>States</hi> Generall, and the Prince his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,</hi> wil take this ſo important a buſines to heart, and not onely be inclineable to the requeſt of the <hi>Adventurers,</hi> but add thereunto other more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary points, ſuch as they in their great Wiſedomes ſhall find fit and neceſſarie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17883:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
